Manish Motwani

School of Electrical Engineering & Computer Science
Oregon State University
Room 3043, Kelley Engineering Center
2500 NW Monroe Ave, Corvallis, OR 97331-5501, USA

motwanim@oregonstate.edu

+1-413-406-8552

https://mmotwani.com/

Research Interests

My broad research interests focus on improving software engineers' productivity by automating software engineering practices. My research involves analyzing large software repositories to learn interesting phenomena, and to use that knowledge to design novel automation techniques, such as requirements elicitation, testing, and program repair.

Education

University of Massachusetts Amherst			
May 2018 Master of Science in Computer Science			
International Institute of Information Technology, Hyderabad			
May 2011 Bachelor of Technology (Honors) in Computer Science and Engineering			
Work Experience			
School of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science, Oregon State University Corvallis, OR, USA Sept 2023 – Present Assistant Professor (tenure-track)			
School of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science, Oregon State University Corvallis, OR, USA Sept 2022 – Aug 2023 Courtesy Faculty Appointment			
College of Computing – School of Computer Science, Georgia Institute of Technology Atlanta, GA, USA Aug 2022 – Aug 2023 Postdoctoral Fellow			
Manning College of Information and Computer Sciences, University of Massachusetts . Amherst, MA, USA Sept 2015 – July 2022 Research Assistant			
SECURITY TOOLS GROUP, ONE ENGINEERING SYSTEMS, MICROSOFT			
Tata Research Development and Design Centre			
CISCO SYSTEMS INDIA PVT. LTD			

SCHOOL OF ELECTRICAL ENGINEERING AND COMPUTER SCIENCE, OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY Corvallis, OR, USA

Instructor (CS 569: Selected Topics in Software Engineering: Program Analysis and Evaluation)

Instructor (CS 563: Software Evolution and Maintenance)

Manish Motwani Curriculum Vitae

Teaching Experience

Spring 2024 Winter 2024 Manning College of Information and Computer Sciences, University of Massachusetts . Amherst, MA, USA

Fall 2021 Guest lecturer (CS 520: Theory and Practice of Software Engineering)
Spring 2020 Guest lecturer (CS 520: Theory and Practice of Software Engineering)
Fall 2018 Teaching Assistant (CS 520: Theory and Practice of Software Engineering)

Tata Research Development and Design Centre Pune, MH, India

May 2013 Guest lecturer (Modelling business processes using the Web Ontology Language (OWL))

Spring 2011 Teaching Assistant (CEG421: Building Energy Simulation)

Fall 2010 Teaching Assistant (CS3155: Compilers)
Fall 2009 Teaching Assistant (MA3200: Discrete Maths)

Publications

Referred Journal/Conference Publications

- Ruikai Huang, **Manish Motwani**, Idel Martinez, and Alessandro Orso, Generating REST API Specifications through Static Analysis. In *proceedings of the research track at the 46th International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE)*, Lisbon, Portugal, April 2024. ACM artifact badges granted: Artifact Available, Artifact Reusable. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1145/3597503.3639137
- Manish Motwani and Yuriy Brun, Better Automatic Program Repair by Using Bug Reports and Tests Together. In proceedings of the technical track at the 45th International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE), pages 1225–1237, Melbourne, Australia, May 2023. ACM artifact badges granted: Artifact Available, Artifact Reusable. DOI: 10.1109/ICSE48619.2023.00109
- Manish Motwani and Yuriy Brun, Understanding Why and Predicting When Developers Adhere to Code-Quality Standards. In proceedings of the Software Engineering in Practice track at the 45th International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE-SEIP), pages 432–444, Melbourne, Australia, May 2023. DOI: 10.1109/ICSE-SEIP58684.2023.00045
- Manish Motwani, Mauricio Soto, Yuriy Brun, René Just, and Claire Le Goues, Quality of Automated Program Repair on Real-World Defects, *IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering (TSE)*, 2020. DOI: 10.1109/TSE.2020.2998785
- **Manish Motwani** and Yuriy Brun, Automatically Generating Precise Oracles from Structured Natural Language Specifications. In *proceedings of the technical track at the 41st International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE)*, pages 188–199, Montreal, QC, Canada, May 2019. ACM artifact badges granted: Artifact Available, Artifact Reusable. DOI: 10.1109/ICSE.2019.00035
- Afsoon Afzal, **Manish Motwani**, Kathryn T. Stolee, Yuriy Brun, and Claire Le Goues, SOSRepair: Expressive Semantic Search for Real-World Program Repair, *IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering (TSE)*, 2019. DOI: 10.1109/TSE.2019.2944914
- Manish Motwani, Sandhya Sankaranarayanan, René Just, and Yuriy Brun, Do Automated Program Repair Techniques Repair Hard and Important Bugs?, In proceedings of the Journal First track at the 40th International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE), pages 25, Gothenburg, Sweden, May 2018.
- Manish Motwani, Sandhya Sankaranarayanan, René Just, and Yuriy Brun, Do Automated Program Repair Techniques Repair Hard and Important Bugs?, *Empirical Software Engineering (EMSE)*, 2018. DOI: 10.1007/s10664-017-9550-0

Referred Short Conference Publications

- Manish Motwani, High-Quality Automated Program Repair. In companion proceedings of the IEEE/ACM 43rd International Conference on Software Engineering: (ICSE-Companion), pages 309–314, Virtual (originally in Madrid, Spain), May 2021. DOI: 10.1109/ICSE-Companion52605.2021.00134.
- Smita Ghaisas, Manish Motwani, Balaji Balasubramaniam, Anjali Gajendragadkar, Rahul Kelkar, and Harrick

Vin. Towards automating the security compliance value chain. In proceedings of the Industrial Track at the 10^{th} Joint Meeting on Foundations of Software Engineering (FSE), pages 1014–1017, Bergamo, Italy, August 2015. DOI: 10.1145/2786805.2804435

• Smita Ghaisas, **Manish Motwani**, and Preethu Rose. Detecting System Use Cases and Validations from Documents. In proceedings of the New Ideas and Emerging Results Track at the 28th IEEE/ACM International Conference on Automated Software Engineering (ASE), pages 568–573, Palo Alto, CA, USA, November 2013. DOI: 10.1109/ASE.2013.6693114

Dissertation

• Manish Motwani. High-Quality Automatic Program Repair 2022. Doctoral Dissertations. 2696. University of Massachusetts, Amherst MA USA. DOI: 10.7275/30288519

Referred Workshop Publications

• Preethu R. Anish, SK. Sharma, **Manish Motwani**, and Smita Ghaisas. Knowledge-assisted Product Requirements Configurator. In *proceedings of the 4th International workshop on Product Line Approaches in Software Engineering (PLEASE*), pages 29–32, San Francisco, CA, USA, May 2013. DOI: 10.1109/PLEASE.2013.6608660

Patents

- Smita Ghaisas, **Manish Motwani**, Preethu R. Anish, Balaji Balasubramaniam, and Aarthy Krishnamurthy. Systems and Methods for an Automated Interpretation of Legal Regulations. United States Patent # US9972016B2, May 2018.
- Smita Ghaisas, Manish Motwani, Preethu Rose Anish, and Shashi Kant Sharma. Automated Classification of Business Rules from Text. United States Patent # US10146762B2, Dec 2018.

Research Mentoring

- Aakash Kulkarni (2^{nd} year MS in CS, Oregon State) Analyzing Faults in REST APIs for Automated Fault Localization, April 2024 – Present.
- Rahil Mehta (1st year MS in CS, Oregon State)
 Automated testing of AI agents using Fuzzing, Jan 2024 Present.
- Aakash Tulso Ramrakhiani (1st year MS in CS, Oregon State)
 Combining Fault Localization Techniques Using Unsupervised Learning Methods, Sept 2023 Present.
- Matthew Davis $(2^{nd}$ year PhD in CS, Georgia Tech) **Heterogenous Memory Bug Detection in High-Performance Computing Applications**, Jan 2024 – Present.
- Ruikai Huang (3^{rd} year PhD in CS, Georgia Tech) Generating REST API Specifications through Static Analysis, Sept 2022 – Aug 2023.
- Jerry Chen (1st year MS in CS, Georgia Tech)
 Heterogenous Memory Bug Detection in High-Performance Computing Applications, Jan 2023 Aug 2023.
- Declan Gray-Mullen (1^{st} year MS in CS, UMass Amherst)

 Detecting and Fixing Flaky Tests using the Source Code Coverage, Sept 2021 Dec 2021.
- Pracheta B Amarnath (2^{nd} year MS in CS, UMass Amherst) Neural-Network-based Automated Program Repair, Sept 2019 – Dec 2019.
- Dilip C. Kavarthapu (2^{nd} year MS in CS, UMass Amherst) and Nishant Yadav (4^{th} year PhD in CS, UMass Amherst) Automated Detection of Fake News from News Articles, Sept 2018 Dec 2018
- Sandhya Sankaranarayanan (1st year MS in CS, UMass Amherst)
 Do Automated Program Repair Techniques Repair Hard and Important Bugs?, Sept 2015 May 2016.

Priya Wagh, Madhuri Jadhav, and Nidhi Zanwar (1st year BS students in CS, MIT Pune)
 Purpose-Centric Search for Enterprise Knowledge Reuse, Aug 2012 – April 2013.

Technical Skills

- Research & Planning: Identifying Problems, Gathering Information, Developing Evaluations, Calculating Results
- Programming languages: Working knowledge of Java, C, C++, C#, Python, Shell, R, Ruby, and PHP
- Machine learning frameworks: PyTorch, Keras/Tensorflow
- Databases: MySQL, Oracle, Kusto
- Integrated Development Environments and tools: Eclipse, NetBeans, MS Visual Studio, Vim, Git, Mercurial
- Cloud platforms: Amazon Web Services, SLURM clusters

Open-Source Software and Software Artifacts

- Respector: Automatically generate REST API specifications in the OpenAPI format using static program analysis. https://github.com/nntzuekai/Respector
- Blues: Information retrieval-based statement-level fault localization for automated program repair. https://github.com/LASER-UMASS/Blues
- RAFL: Combine fault localization results of multiple techniques using unsupervised rank aggregation algorithms. https://github.com/LASER-UMASS/RAFL
- SBIR replication package: Replication package for evaluating SBIR (SBFL and Blues combined using RAFL) and the repair performance of three APR techniques using SBIR on the Defects4J benchmark. https://github.com/LASER-UMASS/SBIR-ReplicationPackage
- JaRFly: Java repair framework. http://JaRFly.cs.umass.edu/
- JaRFly replication package: Replication package of evaluating JaRFly on the Defects4J benchmark. https://github.com/LASER-UMASS/JavaRepair-replication-package
- **Swami**: Automated test generation from natural language software specifications. https://Swami.cs.umass.edu
- **SOSRepair**: Expressive semantic search for real-world program repair. https://github.com/squaresLab/SOSRepair/
- SOSRepair replication package: Replication package for evaluating SOSRepair on the ManyBugs benchmark. https://github.com/squaresLab/SOSRepair-Replication-Package
- Repair Applicability: Data, scripts, and methodology for evaluating the applicability of automated program repair. https://github.com/LASER-UMASS/AutomatedRepairApplicabilityData/

Service

Professional Service

	2024			
PC member	Research track, 34^{th} ACM SIGSOFT International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis (ISSTA)			
Faculty search committee member	Computer Science, Academic Year 2023-24, Oregon State University			
PC member	Research track, 32^{nd} ACM International Conference on the Foundations of Software Engineering (FSE)			
PC member	Industry Government and Communities track, 18^{th} ACM/IEEE Empirical Software Engineering and Measurement (ESEM) conference			
Reviewer	IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering (TSE) journal			
Reviewer Sub–reviewer	IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering (TSE) journal 32^{nd} ACM SIGSOFT International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis (ISSTA)			
Reviewer	IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering (TSE) journal			
Reviewer	ACM Transactions on Software Engineering and Methodology (TOSEM) journal			
Sub–reviewer	43^{rd} ACM/IEEE International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE)			
Reviewer	IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering (TSE) journal			
PC member	Challenge track at the 13^{th} Symposium on Search-Based Software Engineering (SSBSE)			
Reviewer	ACM Transactions on Software Engineering and Methodology (TOSEM) journal			
Reviewer	IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering (TSE) journal			
Sub-reviewer	42^{nd} ACM/IEEE International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE)			
Sub–reviewer	35 th IEEE/ACM International Conference on Automated Software Engineering (ASE)			
Reviewer	IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering (TSE) journal			
Sub-reviewer	41^{st} ACM/IEEE International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE)			
Sub-reviewer	27 th ACM Joint European Software Engineering Conference and Symposium on the Foundations			
	of Software Engineering (ESEC/FSE)			
Sub–reviewer	40^{th} ACM/IEEE International Conference on Software Engineering(ICSE)			
Sub-reviewer	26^{th} ACM Joint European Software Engineering Conference and Symposium on the Foundations			
	of Software Engineering (ESEC/FSE)			
Sub-reviewer	23^{rd} IEEE International Requirements Engineering (RE) conference			

Other Service

	2018			
PhD student representative	Manning College of Information and Computer Sciences, UMass Amherst			
	2017			
Event-coordinator	Indian Students Association (ISA) committee, UMass Amherst			
	2014			
Event-coordinator	Recreational Activities Organization committee, TRDDC, Pune			
Organization committee member	Felicity, annual cultural and technical fest of IIIT Hyderabad			

Formal Presentations

- Better Automatic Program Repair by Using Bug Reports and Tests Together. The Technical Track of the 45th International Conference on Software Engineering(ICSE), Melbourne, Australia, May 2023.
- Understanding Why and Predicting When Developers Adhere to the Code Quality Standards. The Software Engineering in Practice (SEIP) Track of the 45 th International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE), Melbourne, Australia, May 2023.
- **High Quality Automated Program Repair.** The *Doctoral Symposium Track of the 43rd International Conference on Software Engineering(ICSE)*, Virtual (originally Madrid, Spain), May 2021.
- Automatically Generating Precise Oracles from Structured Natural Language Specifications. The Technical Track of the 41st International Conference on Software Engineering(ICSE), Montreal, QC, Canada, May 2019.
- Do Automated Program Repair Techniques Repair Hard and Important Bugs? The *Journal First Track of the* 40^{th} *International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE)*, Gothenburg, Sweden, May 2018.
- **Detecting System Use Cases and Validations from Documents.** The New Ideas and Emerging Results Track of the 28th IEEE/ACM International Conference on Automated Software Engineering (ASE), Palo Alto, CA, USA, Nov 2013.

Professional Associations

Member	Association for Computing Machinery (ACM)	2012 – present
Member	Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE)	2019 – present